Opening Science

Brian A. Nosek

University of Virginia & Center for Open Science, nosek@virginia.edu

Editors’ Commentary

When many people think about ‘open’ their minds jump immediately to notions of free resources, or perhaps to the ability to collectively edit resources, as in the case of Wikipedia entries. Often overlooked in discussions about open are applications to science. In an era where science is plagued by problems such as non-replication, p-hacking, and data fabrication open offers a solution for scientific self-correction. In this chapter, author Brian Nosek showcases a number of ways in which scholarly collaborations and professional societies are using open to improve the quality of research. He focuses especially on evaluating empirical evidence, offering better training, and providing simple incentives for increasing the openness, transparency, and rigor of science.

When my 9 year-old daughter Haven learned about the scientific method in school, she learned that a scientist starts by observing what happens in the world. After collecting enough observations, the scientist generates a question and perhaps a prediction. Then, the scientist designs a study to investigate the question and test the prediction. After collecting data, the scientist learns whether the results are consistent with the prediction or not. Either way, the scientist learns something. The scientist shares the study and data with others so that they can learn too, or try the study themselves to see if they get similar results. Finally, the data are observations for making new questions and predictions.

At dinner, Haven described how her class tried out the scientific method themselves by guessing how many times a coin will show heads when they each flipped it ten times. They observed, predicted, measured, evaluated, shared what they did with the class, collated the observations, and began again. It wasn’t hard, it made sense, and it was completely exciting.

When I said that a lot of science doesn’t actually work that way, Haven was puzzled. What is different? Well, sometimes I don’t share the results of studies we do with others. Why not? Well, they don’t come out the way we expected. But, you still learned something didn’t you? Well, yes, but other scientists are not as interested in those studies. But, isn’t it important for other people to know about when you were wrong so they can learn or try it out themselves? Sure, but it takes a lot of time to share what we did. But, if you aren’t going to share it, then why did you do it? I was running out of answers, and Haven was losing interest.

The ideals of science versus the reality of science

How science is supposed to work and how it actually works are not the same thing. In a survey of more than 3,000 practicing scientists, more than 90% endorsed the norms of science such as transparency, skepticism, and disinterestedness over the counternorms such as secrecy, dogmatism, and self-interestedness.1 When asked how they behaved on a daily basis, fewer but still most scientists said that they behaved more according to the norms than the counternorms. But, when asked how others in their discipline behaved, most respondents perceived their peers to behave according to the counternorms over the norms.

This cynicism about science among scientists is not unfounded. A substantial body of evidence shows that transparency and sharing of data and methodology is the exception rather than the rule,2 and that a variety of suboptimal research practices undermine the integrity and reproducibility of the published literature. Sub-optimal practices include underpowered research designs, selecting reporting of results, and failing to distinguish between exploratory and confirmatory approaches.3

At the same time, the survey revealed that scientists want to behave according to the norms of science. The problem is that the culture of science has skewed the incentives such that researchers perceive that they are not rewarded for transparent, reproducible research, but rather for shaping data − even at the cost of accuracy − to make the most exciting, bold claims possible in order to achieve the reward of publication.4

Origins of the Center for Open Science

It is uncomfortable to be in a culture that is perceived to be misaligned with one’s values. How can we change that? One step is to show that the norms and values are actually shared, even if they are not rewarded in practice. A second step is to make it easy for people to behave according to their values, and particularly to not be punished for doing so. A third step is to surface when people are practicing the valued behaviors to signal to others that it is possible, practical, even prevalent. A fourth step is to show that the counternorms are having negative consequences on the quality of research, providing a means of reinforcing the normative behaviors. And, a final step is to shift the cultural incentives so that they actually support and reinforce the normative behaviors.

Since I joined the faculty at the University of Virginia in 2002, the members of my laboratory have contributed to addressing the first four steps, if only for ourselves. We talk about our scientific values and the practical and cultural barriers to practicing them. We look for ways to address the barriers with existing tools. And, when nothing exists to support the ideals we aim to practice, we create new tools. And, while, the members of my laboratory have no control over the cultural incentives, we also do not accept the status quo. To maintain integrity with our values, we adopted an ethic of pragmatic idealism. What does that mean? Each day, we ask ourselves ‘what can we do today to behave more closely to our ideals while still working and succeeding in the present culture?’

For example, low-powered research is a pervasive problem and increases the likelihood of both false negatives and false positives.5 That is a lose-lose situation. No good that comes from collecting smaller samples than needed to properly evaluate our research questions. To ensure that we conduct properly powered research, we created and maintain a website called Project Implicit to collect data via the internet.6 With an engaging blend of education and research, the site attracts about 1 million participants per year. That was a couple orders of magnitude more successful than we could have anticipated, but it solved our power problem for the kinds of research that could be administered via the web.

In 2006 and 2007, we wrote grants to tackle another gap between our values and practices − transparency. We wanted to improve sharing our research workflow, materials, and data, but the infrastructure didn’t exist to support this practically. Every option we found added a substantial amount of work, and we were already busy enough. We wanted to develop tools so that sharing was a benefit, not a burden. Unfortunately, our grant applications were not sufficiently compelling and they failed. Partly, we may not have had the right pitch, but another challenge might have been that the pitch was ill timed. One reviewer criticized the proposal with a simple point, ‘Researchers don’t like to share their data.’ In 2007, that was a compelling argument. Ultimately, we shelved the idea, and did the best approximation for our sharing goals by using existing tools.7

The idea was re-energized in 2011 when Jeff Spies, a senior member of the laboratory, was choosing among a variety of possible dissertation topics. As a software developer prior to coming to graduate school in quantitative psychology, Jeff had a strong sensibility for building tools that could improve his and others’ research workflow. Jeff recognized that building infrastructure was a very unusual choice for a dissertation topic in psychology, but simultaneously saw huge potential in building tools to make the research lifecycle more transparent. Jeff jumped in with both feet to build and evaluate the Open Science Framework8 as his dissertation project.

At the same time, the lab was starting a study called the Reproducibility Project: Psychology to evaluate the growing concerns about reproducibility of scientific research.9 For this project, we planned to conduct replications of a sample of published studies and compare our findings with the results of the original studies. However, we could not conduct enough replications on our own to get a meaningful sample of studies. So, we opened the project to the research community for anyone to join.

In our good fortune, there were many others with similar interests. Moreover, many were willing to donate some of their time to conducting replications. The project became a collaboration of 50, then 100, then 150 researchers. And, with the alpha version of the Open Science Framework released, we had infrastructure to coordinate the large collaboration and conduct the project transparently.

We didn’t have grant funding, but I had resources to support these projects from giving presentations to organizations about implicit bias, my substantive area of research. Unexpectedly, in the Fall of 2012, the Reproducibility Project: Psychology and Open Science Framework kindled interest from funders that was not present just a few years earlier. Following some press coverage, we were contacted by multiple foundations. After a series of emails, virtual demos, and a visit to Houston, the Laura and John Arnold Foundation gave us a grant for US$5.25 million to launch a non-profit called the Center for Open Science (COS). There had been two self-funded lab projects, and suddenly there was a well-funded non-profit. This might seem a rather abrupt acceleration. Yes, yes it was.

We launched COS with a mission to increase openness, integrity, and reproducibility of scientific research. In its first three years of operation, COS received US$18 million from a combination of private and federal funders to support its mission. The Open Science Framework and Reproducibility Project: Psychology provided a foundation to which we added a full suite of investigations, products, and services to evaluate and improve research practices. COS provides free and open tools and services to the stakeholders in science − funders, journals and publishers, universities, societies, research producers, and research consumers.

COS’s Approach

COS has three teams − metascience, community, and infrastructure − that form the basis of its strategy to increase openness, integrity, and reproducibility of scientific research.

Evidence

The metascience team conducts and supports scientific research about scientific practices. The goal is to accumulate evidence about the problems and opportunities to improve research practices, and to evaluate interventions aiming to address those problems. For example, the Reproducibility Project: Psychology estimated the reproducibility rate in a sample of psychology articles and explored predictors of reproducibility. The completed project involved 270 co-authors and included 100 replications.10 That project produced a spin-off Reproducibility Project for cancer biology,11 and related efforts conducting replications of the same research protocols in many labs to examine variability in replicability12 and independent analysis of the same data by many teams to examine variability in analysis decisions and their impact on observed effects.13 These investigations provided insights about the current state of research practices.

COS also empirically evaluates whether its initiatives have an impact on research practices, positive or negative. For example, a recent grant from the National Science Foundation is supporting a randomized trial to evaluate the impact of receiving training to use the Open Science Framework. Research laboratories at University of California-Riverside will be randomly assigned to receive the training or not (and an orthogonal factor will evaluate training on the responsible conduct of research). Likewise, we evaluated the impact of one of our first and simplest initiatives to incentivize openness – offering badges on journal articles to signal open practices.14 The journal Psychological Science adopted badges to signal open data, open materials, and preregistration on January 1, 2014. From 2012 to 2013, before badges, approximately 3% of the journal’s published articles had open data. After introduction of badges, open data practices increased each half year starting in 2014 reaching 38% of published articles in the first half of 2015. Comparison journals maintained very low data sharing rates across the entire time period. Direct evidence for the effectiveness of initiatives to improve openness will facilitate their adoption and impact.

Training

Researchers possess the values of transparency and reproducibility but if they do not have appropriate training, they may not be able to translate them into practice. The community team produces articles or chapters providing guidance on reproducible practices.15 The team also creates and maintains free text and video content on the Open Science Framework for improving reproducibility and transparency, and conducts webinars and on-site trainings for laboratories, departments, and other research groups. Finally, the team offers free one-on-one virtual consulting to address statistical or methodological challenges related to reproducible research.

Incentives

Even the combination of values and training may not be sufficient for increasing openness and reproducibility in daily practice. Academic researchers are busy and have significant pressures to be productive and publish in order to be competitive for jobs, earn tenure, and advance in their careers. Without realigning the incentives shaping researchers’ behavior, even the best interventions may not stick. The community team works with stakeholders in the scientific community – particularly funders and journals/publishers – to strengthen incentives for open, reproducible practices.

Badges to acknowledge open practices are a simple, low-risk, low-cost nudge toward openness.16 Badges offer no onerous requirements of journal or authors, they just offer an opportunity for authors to signal that they met specifications for open data, open materials, or preregistration.17 Badges also offer an opportunity for journals to signal that such practices are valued, even if they do not directly impact publication decisions.

Registered Reports shift publishing incentives more fundamentally to address publication and reporting biases.18 For journals that adopt Registered Reports, authors can submit the introduction and methodology for peer review before the research is conducted. Peer reviewers evaluate the importance of the research question and the quality of the methodology that will investigate it. The journal provides in-principle acceptance to submissions that survive review.19 After that, the researchers collect the data, analyze it, and report what they found. As long as they conduct the methodology effectively, the results are published whatever the outcome. In standard peer review, the incentives focus on having beautiful results, even at the cost of accuracy. In Registered Reports peer review, the incentives drive researchers to ask the most important questions and have the most beautiful methodology to evaluate those questions. Already more than 20 journals have adopted Registered Reports, and COS facilitated publication of a special issue of Social Psychology in 2014 demonstrating the viability of the approach.20

Another approach to shifting the incentives is to directly incorporate incentives for transparency and reproducibility into publication and funding. The Teaching of Psychology (TOP) Guidelines achieve this by defining eight modular transparency standards for journals and funders to adopt as policies for their authors and grantees.21 The guidelines also ease the barrier to adoption by having multiple levels of stringency so that journals and funders choose to nudge toward openness, or make a bolder requirement of their authors and grantees, depending on the circumstances for their journal or discipline. As of early 2016, more than 50 organizations and 500 journals were signatories to the TOP Guidelines.22

One of the TOP Guidelines is preregistration of analysis plans to promote a clear distinction between confirmatory and exploratory research.23 Preregistration is the law in clinical trials, but is relatively unknown in basic or preclinical sciences. Of the variety of new practices to promote transparency and reproducibility, preregistration may have the highest barrier to entry because it requires actions that are different from most researchers’ current practices. It is common practice to ‘plan’ one’s analysis strategy while conducting the analysis itself. This is fraught with risks of reasoning and reporting biases because analysis decisions can be influenced by the observation of the data.24 In order to stimulate researchers’ interest in trying out preregistration, COS launched the Preregistration Challenge25, 26 a contest in which 1,000 researchers will earn US$1,000 each for publishing their preregistered studies. The Challenge is designed as an education campaign to increase awareness and knowledge about preregistration, and initiate the behavior to possibly instill preregistration as a habit. In sum, COS develops and evaluates a variety of initiatives to strengthen the incentives for open and reproducible practices among active researchers.

Infrastructure

Supporting all of COS’s initiatives is the infrastructure to make transparency easy and practical. The Open Science Framework27 is an open source framework to connect the services that researchers use, and provide an easy means of storing, archiving, preserving, and sharing one’s research data, materials, and workflow. Researchers use the OSF as a virtual workspace to manage their projects with their collaborators. By default, the projects and materials associated with them are private – available only to those individuals that the researcher designates. At any point, the researchers can choose to make parts or all of their project publicly accessible. The flexibility integrates the researchers public and private workflows and removes the practical barriers to openness, replacing them with only the question of whether one wishes to share. Simultaneously, the OSF offers tools to preregister studies, share pre-prints of articles or other research objects, and connect the storage services (e.g., Dropbox, GitHub, institutional repositories) and other tools that researchers use (e.g., citation managers, analysis tools, data collection mechanisms, publication systems) into a single environment. Coupled with COS projects like SHARE28 − an effort to create an open dataset of all research content – we are creating public goods infrastructure that supports the entire research lifecycle.

Cultural Change

COS aims to provide support for evidence-based changes that will align scientific practices with scientific values, and ultimately improve the efficiency of knowledge accumulation and its application to advancing the social good. COS has big goals, but cannot accomplish them itself. Collaboration and collective action are essential. The design of COS as a non-profit developing exclusively free, open-source tools means that COS has no competitors. COS can collaborate with and support others working toward similar ends without concern about competitive disadvantage.

Cultural change is a coordination problem. Many stakeholders need to contribute to shifting cultural norms in concert; initiatives pursued in isolation will falter. All of COS’s initiatives depend on the broader research community supporting, embracing, and even driving changes to research practices and the culture of incentives more broadly. To the extent that COS has succeeded so far, it is largely a consequence of leaders and upstarts in the community supporting the efforts. For example, during the leadership of Eric Eich, Psychological Science initiated a variety of new initiatives including adopting badges for open practices. Also, via leadership of Alan Kraut, Sarah Brookhart, Bobbie Spellman, and many others, the Association for Psychological Science has supported COS efforts – such as adopting Registered Reports at Perspectives on Psychological Science – and other cultural changes. More generally, many researchers share our desire for change, and have been acting on their own, in collaboration with others, and in connection with COS.

The only competition that COS faces is the power of inertia and the status quo. Cultural change is hard, even when everyone agrees that change is needed. However, as 2016 begins, my simple assessment is not ‘Change is possible’ or ‘Change is coming,’ it is ‘Change is happening.’ Across the sciences, funders, journals, societies, universities, and researchers are taking on the task of identifying, testing, evaluating, and implementing changes to research practice to improve the quality and efficiency of research. Incentives are shifting toward embracing transparency and reproducibility as evidence of good practice.

But change is not complete. Researchers, particularly early-career ones, may find the uncertainties in the shifting culture unsettling. I find it exciting and liberating. The culture of incentives had previously been stacked against what most researchers believe is good practice and best for science. Now, the door is open for change and stakeholders across the scientific community are supporting that change.

We worry about kids losing interest in science as a cost to advancing knowledge and having an informed citizenry. To solve the problem, we look for ways to change their minds, and most efforts aren’t working. Perhaps we instead need to focus on changing ourselves. I almost killed Haven’s budding interest in science by describing how it actually works. As those realities shift, I can cultivate Haven’s interest by showing how those scientific ideals that she is learning in 3rd grade are borne out in the daily practice of scientists around the world.

Acknowledgements

Preparation of this chapter was supported by the Laura and John Arnold Foundation, John Templeton Foundation, and the National Institute of Aging.

Notes

1 Anderson Martinson & Vries, 2007.

2 Iqbal, Wallach, Khoury, Schully & Ioannidis, 2016; Miguel et al., 2014; Wicherts, Borsboom, Kats & Molenaar, 2006.

3 Button et al., 2013; Ioannidis, Munafo, R, Fusar-Poli, Nosek & David, 2014; Open Science Collaboration, 2015; Simmons, Nelson & Simonsohn, 2011.

4 Nosek, Spies & Motyl, 2012.

5 Button et al., 2013.

6 Implicit Harvard, n.d.

7 Dataverse, n.d.

8 Open Science Framework, n.d.

9 Open Science Collaboration, 2012.

10 Open Science Collaboration, 2015.

11 Errington et al., 2014.

12 Ebersole et al., 2016; Klein et al., 2014.

13 Silberzahn et al., 2016.

14 Kidwell et al., 2016.

15 Open Science Collaboration, 2016.

16 Kidwell et al., 2016.

17 Open Education Badges, n.d.

18 Open Education Reports, n.d.

19 Chambers et al., 2014.

20 Nosek & Lakens, 2014.

21 Nosek et al., 2015.

22 TOP Guidelines, n.d.

23 Wagenmakers et al., 2012.

24 Gelman & Loken, 2014; Simmons, Nelson & Simonsohn, 2011.

25 Preregistration Challenge, n,d,

26 COS, n.d.

27 Open Science Framework, n.d.

28 SHARE, n.d.

References

Anderson, M. S., Martinson, B. C., De Vries, R. (2007). Normative dissonance in science: Results from a national survey of U.S. scientists. Journal of Empirical Research on Human Research Ethics, 2, 3–14. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1525/jer.2007.2.4.3

Button, K. S., Ioannidis, J. P. A., Mokrysz, C., Nosek, B. A., Flint, J., Robinson, E. S. J., & Munafo, M. R. (2013). Power failure: Why small sample size undermines the reliability of neuroscience. Nature Reviews Neuroscience, 14, 1−12. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn3475

Chambers, C. D., Feredoes, E., Muthukumaraswamy, S. D., & Etchells, P. J. (2014). Instead of “playing the game” it is time to change the rules: Registered Reports at AIMS Neuroscience and beyond. AIMS Neuroscience, 1, 4−17. DOI: https://doi.org/10.3934/neuroscience2014.1.4

Dataverse. (n.d.). Available at https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/bnosek

Ebersole, C. R., Atherton, O. E., Belanger, A. L., Skulborstad, H. M., Allen, J. M., Banks, J. B., Baranski. B., Bernstein, M. J., Bonfiglio, D. B. V., Boucher, L., Brown, E. R., Budiman, N. I., Cairo, A., Capaldi, C., Chartier, C. R., Cicero, D. C., Coleman, J. A., Conway, J., Davis, W. E., Devos, T., Dopko, R. L., Grahe, J., German, K., Hicks, J. A., Hermann, A., Humphrey, B., Johnson, D. J., Joy-Gaba, J., Juzeler, H., Klein, R. A., et al. (2016). Many Labs 3: Evaluating participant pool quality across the academic semester via replication. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 67, 68−82.

Errington, T. M., Iorns, E., Gunn, W., Tan, F., Lomax, J., & Nosek, B. A. (2014). An open investigation of the reproducibility of cancer biology research. eLife, 3:e04333. DOI: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.04333

Gelman, A., & Loken, E. (2014). The statistical crisis in science. American Scientist, 102, 460. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1511/2014.111.460

Ioannidis, J. P. A., Munafo, M. R., Fusar-Poli, P., Nosek, B. A., & David, S. P. (2014). Publication and other reporting biases in cognitive sciences: Detection, prevalence, and prevention. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 18, 235−241. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2014.02.010

Iqbal, S. A., Wallach, J.D., Khoury, M.J., Schully, S.D., Ioannidis, J. P. A. (2016). Reproducible Research Practices and Transparency across the Biomedical Literature. PLoS Biology, 14(1), e1002333. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1002333

Kidwell, M. et al. (2016). Offering badges increases availability of research materials and data. Unpublished manuscript.

Klein, R. A., Ratliff, K. A., Vianello, M., Adams, R. B., Jr., Bahník, Š., Bernstein, M. J., Bocian, K., Brandt, M., Brooks, B., Brumbaugh, C., Cemalcilar, Z., Chandler, J. J., Cheong, W., Davis, W. E., Devos, Theirry, Eisner, M., Frankowska, N., Furrow, D., Galliani, E. M., Hasselman, F., Hicks, J. A., Hovermale, J. F., Hunt, S. J., Huntsinger, J. R., Ijzerman, H., John, M-S., Joy-Gaba, J., Kappes, H., Krueger, L. E., Kurtz, J. (2014). Investigating variation in replicability: A “many labs” replication project. Social Psychology, 45, 142−152. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1027/1864–9335/a000178

Miguel, E., Camerer, C., Casey, K., Cohen, J., Esterling, K. M., Gerber, A., Glennerster, R., Green, D. P., Humphreys, M., Imbens, G., Laitin, D., Madon, T., Nelson, L., Nosek, B. A., Petersen, M., Sedlmayr, R., Simmons, J. P., Simonsohn, U. Van der Laan, M. (2014). Promoting transparency in social science research. Science, 343, 30−31. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1245317

Nosek, B. A., Alter, G., Banks, G. C., Borsboom, D., Bowman, S. D., Breckler, S. J., Bucj, S., Chambers, C. D., Chin, G., Christensen, G., Contestabile, M., Dafoe, A., Eich, E., Fresse, J., Glennerster, R., Goroff, D., Green, D. P., Hesse, B., Humphreys, M., Ishiya, J., Karlan, D., Kraut, A., Lupia, A., Mabry, P., Madon, T., Malhotra, N., Mayo-Wilson, E., McNutt, M., Miguel, E., Levey Paluck, E., et al (2015). Promoting an open research culture. Science, 348, 1422−1425. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aab2374

Nosek, B. A., & Lakens, D. (2014). Registered reports: A method to increase the credibility of published results. Social Psychology, 45, 137−141. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1027/1864–9335/a000192

Nosek, B. A., Spies, J. R., & Motyl, M. (2012). Scientific utopia: II. Restructuring incentives and practices to promote truth over publishability. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 7, 615−631. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1177/1745691612459058

Open Science Collaboration. (2015). Estimating the Reproducibility of Psychological Science. Science, 349(6251), aac4716. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aac4716.

Open Science Collaboration. (2012). An open, large-scale, collaborative effort to estimate the reproducibility of psychological science. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 7, 657−660. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1177/1745691612462588

Open Science Framework. (n.d.). Available at http://osf.io/

Open Science Framewordk Badages. (n.d.). Available at https://osf.io/tvyxz/wiki/home

Open Science Framework Reports. (n.d.). Available at https://osf.io/8mpji/wiki/home/

Project Implicit. (n.d.). Available at http://implicit.harvard.edu/

Preregistration Challenge. (n.d.). Available at http://cos.io/prereg/

SHARE. (n.d.). Available at http://osf.io/share/

Silberzahn, R., Uhlmann, E. L., Martin, D. P., Anselmi, P., Aust, F., Awtrey, E. Bahnik, S., Bai, F., Bannard, C., Bonnier, E., Carlsson, R., Cheung, F., Christensen, G., Clay, R., Craig, M. A., Dalla Rosa, A., Dam, L., Evans, M. H., Flores Cervantes, I., Fong, N., Gamez-Djokic, M., Glenz, A., Gordon-McKeon, S., Heaton, T. J., Hedros Eriksson, K., Heene, M., Holfelich Mohr, A. J., Hogden, F., Hui, K., Johannesson, M., et al. (2016). Many analysts, one dataset: Making transparent how variations in analytical choices affect results. Retrieved from https://osf.io/j5v8f/

Simmons, J. P., Nelson, L. D., & Simonsohn, U. (2011). False positive psychology: Undisclosed flexibility in data collection and analysis allows presenting anything as significant. Psychological Science, 22, 1359–1366.

TOP Guidelines. (n.d.). Available at http://cos.io/top

Wagenmakers, E. J., Wetzels, R., Borsboom, D., van der Maas, H. L., & Kievit, R. A. (2012). An agenda for purely confirmatory research. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 7, 632–638.

Wicherts, J.M., Borsboom, D., Kats, J., & Molenaar, D. (2006). The poor availability of psychological research data for reanalysis. American Psychologist, 61, 726–728. DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0003–066X.61.7.726

How to cite this book chapter:

Nosek, B A. 2017. Opening Science. In: Jhangiani, R S and Biswas-Diener, R. (eds.) Open: The Philosophy and Practices that are Revolutionizing Education and Science. Pp. 89–99. London: Ubiquity Press. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5334/bbc.g. License: CC-BY 4.0

Open-Source for Educational Materials Making Textbooks Cheaper and Better

Ed Diener*, Carol Diener† and Robert Biswas-Diener‡

*University of Virginia

†University of Illinois

‡Noba, robert@nobaproject.com

Editors’ Commentary

Aside from being expensive, traditional textbooks are also rigidly structured, environmentally unfriendly, and unnecessarily long. As a result, although most open textbook projects attempt to produce an openly licensed version of a resource that most faculty will find familiar, authors Ed Diener, Carol Diener, and Robert Biswas-Diener—all affiliated with Noba—set out to do something different. The model that they have created, with leading scholars authoring over 100 brief modules (supported with high quality ancillary resources) that faculty may customize using a user-friendly interface, represents a new and innovative model for open educators in other disciplines. In this chapter the authors discuss their rationale for the Noba project, describe some of its successes and challenges, and share their hopes for the future of open education.

When we reflected on our combined decades working as instructors in academia, we saw strengths in the educational system in which we worked; but also shortcomings. One of the biggest problems that emerged across our tenure as instructors was the rising cost of a college education. There are many reasons why education has become more expensive but one factor that stood out to us was the cost to students of textbooks. We landed on this factor because—unlike cost of living or tuition—it is one that faculty have a direct influence upon. According to The Enterprise Institute1 textbook prices have increased more than 800 per cent since 1978. By contrast, the Consumer Price Index—a measure of variation in the price of common retail goods—has only risen 250% in that same period. The consequences of this are predictable: A US PIRG survey2 of more than 2,000 students from 156 campuses revealed that 65% of the students surveyed indicated that they had decided against buying a required course text because of the expense. Over 90% do so knowing that it could adversely affect their grades. Students Surveys reveal that many students never buy the textbook for a class, and just try to get along without it. In this chapter, we will discuss the problematic landscape of textbooks and relate the story of how we came to address these problems through Noba.

Traditional Textbooks

Textbook prices are kept high by several means:

1. New Editions. First, publishers ask authors to update their books frequently, meaning that older and used books cannot be assigned by professors because they are viewed as ‘out of date.’ Whether the scholarship in various fields that undergraduates need to learn has actually changed enough to warrant continual revisions of textbooks is, in our view, doubtful. One clear example of this can be seen in the instance of the release of the latest Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders.3 Following the publication of the DSM-5 many textbook publishers rushed new introductory psychology books to market that promised special DSM-5 updates. It is not entirely clear, however, that the taxonomic structure or diagnostic criteria for clinical professionals found in the DSM are an important enough influence on introductory undergraduate and high school psychology that a revised book is warranted. While experts might argue over the scale of changes between the DSM-IV and DSM-5 (were they large or small?) there were very few changes that would affect how basic material was introduced to general psychology students. It is possible that the new editions of DSM-5 compatible textbooks reflect a market demand but it is also possible that this is an illustration of the profit driven edition cycle common in academic publishing.

2. Non-traditional economic model. Another factor that keeps textbooks high is that professors select the books, but students pay for them. In our experience this means that instructors really are not price sensitive, and this allows much higher prices than if professors or universities were paying for the books. In a traditional economic model supply and competition would serve to reduce costs. The clearest corollary with the economic model of textbooks—at least in the United States − is prescription medicine. In the US doctors are the ones who often choose the medication but patients are the ones who pay for them. Not surprisingly, prescription medications, according to Consumer Reports,4 are also rising at an alarming rate (1 in 10 medications rose in price by more than 100 per cent over a one year period from 2013−2014).

3. Size. The third factor that makes textbooks prices so lofty is that they try to cover a huge amount of material in an attempt to cover any and every topic that a professor might want. This results in very, very large texts that cover much more material than any student could possibly learn in a single course. So-called brief textbooks are a notable market solution to this problem and, in themselves, a recognition that traditional texts may be too long.

Beyond the issue of expense, we noticed a number of additional problems with traditional textbooks. For one thing, they use a lot of paper, and many students are increasingly comfortable with digital materials, including texts. Although surveys commonly point to the conclusion that the vast majority of students continue to use print textbooks many also find that as many as 30% prefer digital texts5 and 80% find e-books helpful in completing assignments and test preparation.6 Second, textbooks present certain material and present it in a fixed order. Thus, instructors who want to customize their course face a challenge in organizing the materials for students. For decades, instructors have tailored course content to reflect their own preferences and students have endured syllabi that suggest reading ‘Chapter 2’ and then ‘Chapters 4 and 9’ and then ‘Chapter 6.’ Digital texts could easily solve this problem. We also heard professors say that they would like more on certain topics, and coverage of topics that are not in the text they choose. The so-called standard canon—the topics found in many introductory psychology books—appears to preference some historically accepted topics such as hypnosis, while overlooking others such as the current replication crisis, the academic publication process, and knowledge emotions. Again, computer based textbooks offer a solution because they allow professors to add and subtract material from their textbooks. Finally, digital textbooks also allow added features such as embedded learning assignments, videos, interactive simulations and hyperlinks that have the potential for increasing student learning while they read the text.

One final issue related to the cost of traditional textbooks is that many scholarships will cover tuition, but not textbooks. Thus, the students are on their own, and a shocking number of students report not buying the books for all of their classes. This puts needy students at a disadvantage compared to more affluent ones.

Although we see the problems with textbooks we—the authors of this chapter—do not consider ourselves above them. We have assigned traditional textbooks. Instructors buy into the current model of expensive texts sold by commercial publishers for several reasons. One reason is that many of the textbooks are well-written and of reasonably high quality. They contain interesting side bars and high quality graphics. They are well edited. Their popularity is also based on other factors. For instance, professors find it convenient and easy to use commercial texts because they come with a variety of teaching aids such as instructors’ manuals, test banks, and PowerPoint presentations. Last, traditional textbooks are popular for the same reason that some brands of beer are: namely, they are a commercial product at the tip of a large marketing spear. Sales reps send emails, free samples, and drop by the office to answer questions. Some publishers of traditional texts supply faculty with travel grants and other ‘development money.’ Somewhere between the high cost, the inflexible structure, and the lack of student input there is a clear problem in need of a solution.

The Advantages of Digital Textbooks

There are several suggestions alluded to in the previous section. All of them are based on the properties of the digital medium. It might sound strange to focus so heavily on digital in a book about open resources but the truth is ‘digital’ and ‘open’ go hand in glove. In open education circles advocates often talk about an ‘abundance model’ rather than the traditional ‘scarcity model.’ It is the advent of digital technology that allows us to easily create, modify and share materials at an unpresented rate. The proliferation of access to the internet has dovetailed with the gaining traction of the open movement. It is the reason why open exists today and not back when scribes were scratching cuneiform on clay tablets.

Based on the comments above, here is a summary of the advantages of digital (and open-source) texts:

1. Less expensive. Publication costs do not include paper, ink, packaging or shipping. Revisions can be made more easily without rewriting the entire book, and the costs of shipping and printing are negligible. Therefore the notion of ‘revised editions’ can be supplanted by ‘revisions as necessary.’ Even if students choose to print out a hard-copy of their open textbook, or use a print on demand service the costs are much lower than traditional texts. For example, Noba’s textbook ‘Discover Psychology 2.0’ currently retails for less than 15 US dollars plus shipping. Admittedly, it is a softcover, black and white book, but we regularly receive student feedback suggesting this is an acceptable trade.

2. Easier on the environment. Digital texts do not require physical manufacture or shipping.

3. Foreign access. It is much easier to access materials, especially in poor nations where costs are a serious concern. Many economically developing nations have invested in internet infrastructure.

4. Individualization. Instructors can select only the modules he or she wants to cover in a course, and can add or subtract material from chapters. An extension of the idea of individualization is localization. The open format allows instructors around the world to modify content so that it is more relevant and relatable to their students.

5. Alternative chapters can be made available. Digital textbooks can use alternate forms of the same material. For example, a text might offer an overview chapter on ‘The Brain and Nervous System’ but also offer more specialized units on ‘Neurons’ and ‘The Biochemistry of Love.’

6. Active learning. The digital format offers a variety of methods for increasing in the moment learning including “mouse overs” (e.g., definitions pop up on screen), ‘adaptive learning’ (tests embedded in the chapter that track individual student performance and adapt to it), and hyperlinks to related videos and readings.

7. Accessibility. The open format has fewer restrictions regarding printing, copy and pasting, sharing, and re-sizing—to name a few—which means that these resources support assistive learning for students who need accommodation.

The Noba Model

Two of us (ED and CD) decided to fund Noba because of the problems we saw with the current textbook model. We felt comfortable focusing our efforts exclusively on psychology because it is considered a high enrollment course with a large potential for student savings. Our initial idea was to have experts for each topic in psychology write chapters on their respective areas. For example, we received our chapter on ‘Eyewitness testimony’ from Elizabeth Loftus and our chapter on ‘Evolutionary theories in psychology’ from David Buss. By focusing exclusively on our own area of expertise (psychology), and by investing in a model that emphasizes expert created content we have largely been able to side step some of the common skepticism of quality faced by many OERs. In fact, we have developed a sophisticated quality assurance program that includes:

1. Expert created content.

2. Editorial review.

3. Peer review.

4. Student review.

5. International review.

6. Accessibility review.

7. Empirical review.

We also opted for a modular approach in which instructors could drag and drop each chapter in which they were interested into a unique course textbook and assign it only to their own students. We created 100 different modules ranging from ‘research methods’ to ‘creativity’ to ‘mood disorders’ covering all corners of psychology. The modular approach means that Noba materials can be used either as a collated textbook or as supplemental reading. Of course, all of these materials are Creative Commons licensed and it was our strong intention to make them free for all students.

To generate enthusiasm for Noba we also directed money toward faculty and students in the form of grants and awards, none of which were contingent on using Noba. On the faculty side we awarded grants for the review of our materials and for experimenting with new digital capabilities. For example, because textbooks can now be individualized it is possible that instructors could assign core content and each individual student could select additional chapters that represented his or her own unique interest. It is possible that having 30 unique textbooks in a class of 30 students is a management nightmare for instructors. It is equally possible that this method is an unprecedented means of engaging students and increasing interest. We’ll have to wait until the data are in to see. On the student side we awarded 10 thousand dollars each of two years for the creation of short videos that would become a permanent part of Noba catalog.

It is here, perhaps, that we are most proud of Noba. Earlier digital and open source textbooks were simply electronic versions of traditional textbooks. Because the Noba system is built around modules it is changing the way we think about what a textbook is, what it can do, and how it can impact learning.

Then, an interesting thing happened. Instructors did not flock to our site. Many seemed unmoved by the free price tag. Some refused to mention Noba to their local psychology clubs. Others criticized our experts as being ‘biased.’ We heard first hand reports that sales reps from large publishers were warning faculty members away from open source materials such as Noba, suggesting that they are low quality. It was surprising and unsettling. Ultimately, we interviewed instructors and learned a simple truth: they are dedicated and passionate teachers who are often overworked and who have little reserve energy to evaluate a new text, let alone create new lectures and tests if they adopt one.

Based on this insight we shifted our priorities from textbook creation to instructor support. We collaborated with a large team of experts in both psychology and instructional design to create high quality test banks, instructor manuals and PowerPoint presentations. We created a print on demand version of our textbooks that sells for less than US$15. We partnered with Cerego, an adaptive learning technology company, to embed each of our modules with an adaptive quiz function. We revised many modules so that they employed simpler language and more international examples. We created a blog of practical teaching ideas and offer essays on a variety of teaching topics ranging from teaching large classes to teaching biological psychology. We gave additional grants to instructors to pilot a review of our materials and create rubrics for evaluating Noba that can be used by individual instructors and departments both. We ensured that our materials were accessible to those with visual impairments and other disabilities. In essence, we tried to think of every small concern or headache an instructor might face in deciding whether to adopt Noba and deal with it. And, if it was not clear before, it’s all free to all of our users.

The result of our efforts is—three years in—visible. We are being officially adopted at two and four year institutions such as Northwest Vista College (a 2-year institution using Noba with approximately 1,500 students a year), West Virginia University (approximately 3,000 students a year), and East Georgia State University (an institution that reports US$114 per student in savings.7 We are being recommended by our colleagues and are receiving higher satisfaction and engagement ratings from our users. Most importantly, we have saved students—using a conservative estimate—more than two million dollars in textbook fees.

We also track out impact qualitatively through feedback be receive from instructors and departments that use Noba. Here are two such examples that highlight both the financial and pedagogic benefits:

‘Teaching with Noba gives me freedom as an instructor. It gives me freedom to assign as little or as much to my students as I would like. It gives me freedom to supplement my teaching rather than overshadow it. It gives me the freedom of knowing my students (some of the poorest in the nation) are not falling behind because they are waiting on financial aid to come through.’ –Raechel Soicher, Linn-Benton Community College

‘I am thrilled that we have such a wonderful resource for our students. We have over 3,000 Introduction to Psychology students each year at WVU and you can imagine how much money this saves our students. Even after the semester is in its 2nd week we have students asking where to buy the textbook. It’s nice to remind them that the resource is free.’ – Constance Toffle, West Virginia University

The Future of Open Education

The cost of college education has been spiraling upward, and textbooks are one part of this trend. Textbooks are much more expensive than they need to be, and open-source texts are one solution to the problem. Furthermore, the digital format has the potential to radically transform the way that texts are used as instructional aids and we are only beginning to scratch the surface of this potential. In the future, instructors will better be able to modify the actual text, the examples, and the featured research contained within modules. To some degree, that very concept is anathema to academic culture. Many professors place a premium on their intellectual property and value their own authorial voice. The notion that someone else might tinker with that can—admittedly—be unsettling. Rather than simply dismissing the idea of open-source collaboration future educators must engage in a discussion about how this process can occur while still preserving the scientific rigor we all prize so highly.

It is our hope that in the near future we will see a sea change in the attitudes of individuals and institutions regarding open materials. We would like to see a day where high quality open materials are the standard and students must opt out to purchase additional resources. Boards of trustees, university administration, alumni groups, student groups, and even legislatures can bring pressure to bear to use cheaper textbook alternatives. Many are fearful of seeming to tread on academic freedom, but selecting from among the less expensive open-source textbooks does not truly limit in any way the material they cover in their courses—and this is what academic freedom is.

Notes

1 Weissmann, 2013.

2 Senack, 2014.

3 American Psychiatric Association, 2013.

4 Consumer Reports, 2015.

5 Bolkan, 2015.

6 Falc, 2013.

7 Affordable Learning Georgia, 2016.

References

Affordable Learning Georgia. (2016). Textbook transformation grants: Round one projects gallery fall 2014 – spring 2015. Retrieved from http://www.affordablelearninggeorgia.org/site/round1

American Psychiatric Association. (2013). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (5th ed.). Washington, DC: Author.

Bolkan, J. (2015). Survey: Most students prefer traditional texts over e-books. Retrieved from https://campustechnology.com/articles/2015/09/01/survey-most-students-prefer-traditional-texts-over-ebooks.aspx

Consumer Reports. (2015). Are you paying more for your Rx meds? A consumer reports’ poll shows one-third of Americans hit by high drug prices. Retrieved from http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/news/2015/08/are-you-paying-more-for-your-meds/index.htm

Falc, E. O. (2013). An assessment of college students’ attitudes towards using an online e-textbook. Interdisciplinary Journal of E-Learning and Learning Objects, 9, 1−12.

Senack, E. (2014). Fixing the broken textbook market: How students respond to high textbook costs and demand alternatives. Retrieved from http://uspirg.org/sites/pirg/files/reports/ NATIONAL%20Fixing%20Broken%20Textbooks%20Report1.pdf

Weissmann, J. (2013, January 3). Why are college textbooks so absurdly expensive? The Atlantic. Retrieved from http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2013/01/why-are-college-textbooks-so-absurdly-expensive/266801/

How to cite this book chapter:

Diener, E, Diener, C and Biswas-Diener, R. 2017. Open-Source for Educational Materials Making Textbooks Cheaper and Better. In: Jhangiani, R S and Biswas-Diener, R. (eds.) Open: The Philosophy and Practices that are Revolutionizing Education and Science. Pp. 209–217. London: Ubiquity Press. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5334/bbc.p. License: CC-BY 4.0

TeachPsychScience.org: Sharing to Improve the Teaching of Research Methods

David B. Strohmetz*, Natalie J. Ciarocco and Gary W. Lewandowski, Jr.

Monmouth University

*dstrohme@monmouth.edu

Editors’ Commentary

Designing a course to be engaging can be challenging, especially when the course in question is one that students often dread having to take and traditional sources of inspiration are limited, static, uneven in quality, or cost-prohibitive. In this chapter, authors David Strohmetz, Natalie Ciarocco, and Gary Lewandowski discuss the development of a website devoted to the sharing of openly-licensed and peer-reviewed strategies and demonstrations for teaching research methods and statistics. In doing so they demonstrate how individual faculty can marry the recognized resources and practices of their discipline, such as support from professional societies and peer review, with open licensing to be able to ‘take a little piece of their world and improve it.’

Teaching research methods and statistics can be frustrating. The courses that are foundational to the undergraduate major, and psychological science in general, are the very ones that students often dread or avoid taking.1 Even when they do take these classes, they do not necessarily see the value of this newly gained knowledge.2 Hence, faculty teaching research methods or statistics in psychology often start every semester with a class full of less than enthusiastic students. This attitude does not seem to impede their learning. Most students achieve a baseline mastery of the material, but still leave the class with poor attitudes about statistics and research, and an inability to see their usefulness.3 This puts faculty in a unique position. Perhaps more so than in any other course, faculty need support in improving students’ learning experiences in these classes. In this chapter, we will describe our initiatives to support engaging research methods teaching, one of which is TeachPsychScience.org, an open-access resource to support teaching research methods and statistics.

The Challenge

When each of us first began teaching research methods and statistics, we experienced the same problem that many new instructors face. How should I structure my classes to make them both engaging and educational? How can I best promote student enthusiasm for the course? Initially, we did what we imagine other instructors do. We spent time reviewing textbooks, adopting ones that we thought students would find engaging and illuminating. We then constructed our lectures based on the content covered in each chapter, making sure that students memorized the terminology and mastered key concepts. As we gained experience from teaching these courses multiple times, we started to experience a restlessness in our approach. Importantly, the course was not broken or going terribly. In fact, the course was going well. Yes, students were learning. Yes, students gave us favorable course evaluations. However, they were not displaying the same passion for psychological science as we have.

After numerous conversations with our colleagues and soul searching, we began to realize that part of the problem was our approach to teaching. While our students were learning methodological and statistical concepts, they really were not engaging in the process of psychological science. We knew the value of active learning and wanted to include more in our classes, but we had a problem. High-quality teaching demonstrations, activities, and other similar resources to support our teaching of research methods and statistics were extremely limited. There are resources available, but each can be problematic for various reasons.

Instructor Manuals

One possible place to find these things are the instructor’s manuals that accompany methods or statistics textbooks. There are several limitations to relying on instructor manuals. First, the purpose of these manuals is to facilitate the integration of the textbook into one’s course, not necessarily improve the overall quality of learning and engagement in the scientific process in that course. No text is perfectly comprehensive so there were often topics we include in our classes which are not necessarily covered in the text. Second, the quality of the activities and other materials in instructor manuals is uneven, limiting their utility. If the instructor materials simply reiterate the book’s content, it is hard to truly broaden students’ exposure to the material and mastery of the skills. Part of the issue may be that the instructor’s resource authors tend to be different from the textbook authors and therefore may not be as experienced in teaching the course. The third problem is that even if a textbook has a quality instructor’s manual, it is available only to adopters of that textbook.

Teaching Conferences

Attending national and regional teaching conferences is another way to garner resources. Each of us have gleaned creative teaching demonstrations and strategies from these opportunities. However, few of these conferences focus specifically on teaching methods and statistics. In addition, our limited travel funds meant we had to be judicious in our choices of which conferences to attend.

Teaching Journals

A third resource are teaching-oriented journals such as the Teaching of Psychology and Scholarship of Teaching and Learning in Psychology. These peer-reviewed journals publish a wide range of articles concerning teaching in psychology. Periodically, a compilation of articles specific to teaching research methods and statistics are published. A recent example is the e-book, Teaching Statistics and Research Methods: Tips from ToP,4 freely available through the Society for the Teaching of Psychology (http://teachpsych.org/ebooks/index.php). These resources are invaluable, but searching opportunities for specific types of activities are limited and they are static in their content.

A Little Piece Project

In our department, we have an informal motto, ‘Take a little piece of your world and improve it.’ As we thought about our methods courses, we decided to do more than simply improve the quality of our individual classes. We wanted to take this ‘little piece’ of our world and improve the quality of instruction in research methods and statistics as widely as possible. We discussed ways for strategies for doing this and the type of support that was available for such open-access initiatives.

We started with a small project, capitalizing on the funding and dissemination opportunities provided by the Society for the Teaching of Psychology (STP). STP has an ‘Office of Teaching Resources in Psychology’ (OTRP),5 dedicated to promoting the development of resources for advising and teaching psychology. To facilitate and financially support the development of teaching resources, STP annually offers up to five Instructional Resources Awards. We received one of these awards in 2009 to create a resource for instructors which identifies student-friendly research articles for illustrating various research design elements. We provided instructors with discussion starters and in-class activities to accompany each article. Our goal was to promote the reading of published research studies as students learned about the research process.

We were happy with the result and pleased that we had a means for sharing this open access resource with other instructors via the STP website.6 However, we realized we could do more. Given the static nature of a pdf document, our resource was limited in its ability to be efficiently search for specific demonstration ideas. Likewise, we could not continually update this resource as we found new articles employing interesting or creative research designs. Besides, reading actual research studies is just one way in which students can engage in the process of science.

As our conversations continued, we realized that more often than not, when we needed a teaching idea, we would turn to one of our colleagues. We wondered if we could create a centralized repository where colleagues could easily share their ideas, suggestions, and demonstrations specific to teaching research methods and statistics. This website would be dynamic, allowing the posting of new ideas and teaching activities. It would also be easily searchable and provide opportunities for visitor feedback.

Online repositories to support instruction is not a new idea. MERLOT7 is a very broad and general repository of resources available to instructors across a wide range of disciplines. As each of us teach social psychology, we can access more than 5,000+ links to teaching ideas and resources on Jon Mueller’s ‘Resources for the Teaching of Social Psychology’ website.8 The Social Psychology Network also has a page dedicated to Social Psychology Teaching Resources.9 We wanted to create a similar website to specifically support the teaching of research methods and statistics. This open-access website would be textbook agnostic and continually updated with new contributions, minimizing the limitations of instructor manuals. It will provide an ongoing opportunity for instructors to share the ideas, strategies, and activities they use to facilitate student learning in these courses. The idea of TeachPsychScience.org was born.

TeachPsychScience.org

Creating and maintaining a website is a major undertaking. While one of us had experience with developing a website to support the dissemination of psychological research on relationships to the general public,10 we were starting from scratch in the development of this website. We had several guiding principles for our endeavor. First, the resources available on the website had to be pedagogically sound. This meant that all submitted material would undergo a peer-review process before being posted on the website. Second, the website had to be user-friendly and searchable, making it easy for instructors to identify resources to meet their immediate teaching needs. Third, the website had to be both sustainable and scalable as we wanted this to become a valuable and ever evolving resource for all methods and statistics instructors.

When we considered issues surrounding copyright concerns, we decide to make all of the resources on the website subject to Creative Commons Licensing. We were not interested in monetizing the website; rather we simply wanted to help others become better teachers of statistics and research methods. We believe that instructors should have a right to modify or adapt the resources to meet their particularly teaching situation. Creative Commons Licensing provides this flexibility while still protecting the author from copyright infringement if the resource is used for something other than noncommercial educational purposes.

As we developed our vision for the website, we knew that finding financial support for this venture would be a major challenge. We are fortunate to have professional organizations in psychology which support pedagogical initiatives. We obtained a grant from the Association for Psychological Science (APS) Fund for Teaching and Public Understanding of Psychological Science. This grant funded the development and maintenance of the website for several years. Second, we needed to find a company to both build and host the site. We had a web designer11 work with us to translate our ideas and vision into a viable website. Our goal was to provide a user-friendly website that allowed visitors to find resources in multiple ways, including searching by keywords or category (e.g., experimental designs or factorial analysis of variance). This meant that we had to spend much time planning the organizational structure of the website so that it would be both logical and intuitive to visitors. On the back end, we wanted an administrator interface that we could easy navigate in order to manage and update the content of the website.

Once we created the underlying structure for the website, we needed a core set of resources before we could actually launch TeachPsychScience.org. Drawing upon what we collectively do in our own classes, we created over 50 resources spanning the various categories of resource materials. These resources included class demonstrations, student practice exercises, writing assignments, class/lab activities, and links to other web-based resources supporting the instruction of research methods and statistics. We did not want the site dominated by our own contributions, especially as we wanted to glean ideas from our talented colleagues. We contacted colleagues at other institutions, asking them to submit any activities they used in their methods or statistics classes for inclusion in website. Interestingly, many responded by lamenting that they really did not have any good activities but wished they did. This provided further evidence of the need for the open-access repository we were creating. To expand the resources on the website, we monitored teaching of psychology publications and requested submissions from authors. We promoted the website at teaching conferences and teaching workshops and encouraged presenters and attendees to submit any activities or demonstrations they had to the website.

We believe that a key to the success of TeachPsychScience.org is to only include resources that were of high quality. To achieve this, we established a submission and peer-review process to ensure that all materials posted on the website are pedagogically sound. Having added this traditional peer-review process also provided contributors the justification for including their submissions on their curriculum vitae. We contacted scholars in the field of teaching and learning to serve as initial reviewers for the website. We also offered the position to those who contributed several high-quality submissions. To aid the process for reviewers, we created a rating form to accompany reviews and established some basic instructions for reviewers. With the help of between 5−8 reviewers and a number of additional submissions, we launched the website on June 1, 2010.

Open-access resources are valuable only if they are known and used. Our first challenge was spreading the word of the site’s existence. We contacted other teaching resources sites, asking them to provide a link to TeachPsychScience.org. We advertised the website on various disciplinary websites and at teaching conferences. The site was featured in APA’s Psychology Teacher Network Summer 2010 newsletter and is still promoted on APS’s website. Over the past four and half years, the site has had over 48,000 users, 66% of whom were new visitors. Not surprisingly, traffic tends to be higher at the start of the fall and spring semesters. It is clear that this online repository for open-access resources is meeting a need among research methods and statistics instructors.

The second challenge we face is ongoing. The long-term success and value of TeachPsychScience.org depends on the continual submissions of resources by other instructors. Currently, there are over 100 demonstrations and other teaching ideas available for instructors to incorporate into their classes. The continued utility of this open-access resource depends the instructors sharing their creative ideas for promoting student learning in research methods and statistics. Currently, we rotate as editors for the website every 6 to 12 months. One of us takes the lead as the liaison between submissions and reviewers, makes final decision about the quality of a resource, and manages the site content.

Finally, at some point we will need to identify a stable funding source for the continuation of TeachPsychScience.org. Our initial grant provided financial support for the first five years of the website. We recently secured another grant from APS to support the expansion of the website to include resources to support the teaching of scientific writing. As writing is one of the three pillars of the research process, along with statistics and methodology, we felt this missing aspect was critical to develop and share. The additional funding provides support for material solicitation and development, along with a redesign of the website. The website update will allow for submissions type we did not originally consider (e.g., submissions that necessitate multiple accompanying files), incorporate writing-specific activities, and make the site more mobile friendly. This additional grant funding will also ensure the availability of the TeachPsychScience.org in supporting quality teaching for the next several years. Eventually, we will need to address the long term viability of the website.

Your Piece of the World

TeachPsychScience.org started with a simple desire – our wish to improve how research methods and statistics are taught so that all students may come to love the process of psychological science as much as we do. We are fortunate that the financial support we received first from the Society for the Teaching of Psychology and then the Association of Psychological Science, coupled with the Creative Commons License, brought our desire to fruition. It is through the open sharing of our collective wisdom and experiences that we were able to pick our little piece of the world and improve it as we continue to enhance and strengthen learning as students embrace psychological science.

What piece of the world are you going to improve? The fact of the matter is that anyone can replicate our efforts with TeachPsychScience.org in other areas of psychology. Think of the course you teach, your research expertise, as well as the psychology topics that capture your attention. In each of those areas you likely have something valuable to share with your fellow teachers and the field. If you have resources for teaching methods and statistics, we hope that you will share them with us. But more importantly, we hope that you find ways to extend your influence beyond your own classroom, into the classrooms of your colleagues and ultimately to improving students’ lives.

Notes

1 Rajecki et al., 2005

2 Sizemore & Lewandowski, 2009.

3 Sizemore & Lewandowski, 2009, 2011.

4 Jackson & Griggs, 2012.

5 OTRP, n.d.

6 STP, n.d.

7 MERLOT, n.d.

8 Teaching of Social Psychology, n.d.

9 Social Psychology Teaching Resources, n.d.

10 Science of Relationships, n.d.

11 Invisual, n.d.

References

Invisual. (n.d.). Available at http://www.invisual.us/

Jackson, S. L., & Griggs, R. A. (2012). Teaching statistics and research methods: Tips from ToP. Retrieved from the Society for the Teaching of Psychology Web site: http://teachpsych.org/ebooks/stats2012/index.php

MERLOT. (n.d.). Available at http://www.merlot.org

OTRP. (n.d.). Available at http://teachpsych.org/otrp/index.php

Rajecki, D., Appleby, D., Williams, C., Johnson, K., & Jeschke M. (2005). Statistics can wait: Career plans, activity, and course preferences of American psychology undergraduates. Psychology Learning & Teaching, 4, 83−89. DOI: https://doi.org/10.2304:plat.2004.4.2.83

Science of Relationships. (n.d.). Available at http://www.scienceofrelationships.com/

Sizemore, O. J., & Lewandowski, G. W., Jr. (2009). Learning may not equal liking: How a course in research and statistics changes knowledge but not attitudes. Teaching of Psychology, 36, 90−95. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1080/00986280902739727

Sizemore, O. J., & Lewandowski, G. W., Jr. (2011). Lesson learned: Using clinical examples for teaching research methods. Psychology Learning & Teaching, 10, 25−31. DOI: https://doi.org/10.2304/plat.2011.10.1.25

Social Psychology Teaching Resources. (n.d.). Available at http://www.socialpsychology.org/teaching.htm

STP. (n.d.). Available at http://teachpsych.org/resources/Documents/otrp/resources/ciarocco10.pdf

Teaching of Social Psychology. (n.d.). Available at http://jfmueller.faculty.noctrl.edu/crow/

How to cite this book chapter:

Strohmetz, D B, Ciarocco, N J, and Lewandowski, Jr. G W. 2017. TeachPsychScience.org: Sharing to Improve the Teaching of Research Methods. In: Jhangiani, R S and Biswas-Diener, R. (eds.) Open: The Philosophy and Practices that are Revolutionizing Education and Science. Pp. 237–244. London: Ubiquity Press. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5334/bbc.s. License: CC-BY 4.0